We start, we are on דף פ"ט. Daf Pey Tes. We are
actually right at the very bottom of פ"ח עמוד ב'. Pey Ches
Amud Beis. And we were finishing up some discussions about the מנורה
Menorah because we were talking about one of the measures was the
חצי לוג Chatzi Log for every lamp of the מנורה. Menorah. So
now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay.
רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, it's six lines from the bottom, three words
before the end of the line. רבי יהושע בן קרחה אומר, Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Karchah omer, so the first word is the word קרחה
Karchah now five lines from the bottom, מנורה באה מן הכיכר ואין
מלקחיה ומחתותיה ונרותיה באין מן הכיכר. Menorah ba min hakikar ve-ein melkacheha
u-machtoseha ve-neroseha ba-in min hakikar.
So the question is whether the lamps of the מנורה Menorah were
physically attached to the מנורה, Menorah, like the you know the the
container that held the oil itself at the top of the arm.
So it's obviously a lot easier if they weren't attached, makes a
lot easier to clean them. So that's this opinion right now of
רבי יהושע בן קרחה. Rabbi Yehoshua ben Karchah. And one way in
which this is articulated is when the תורה Torah assigns a כיכר,
Kikar, the תורה Torah says two things by מנורה, Menorah, a כיכר,
Kikar, a talent of gold, and it says that it's מקשה, Mikshah,
that it's beaten, it's one unit. So the assumption here is that
those go together. So רבי יהושע בן קרחה Rabbi Yehoshua ben Karchah
says that only the מנורה Menorah itself came from the כיכר, Kikar,
but the tongs and the like little shovels, the things for scraping
out and cleaning the lamps, and the lamps, did I'm sorry, בא
מן הכיכר Ba min hakikar did not come from the כיכר Kikar
and therefore presumably were also, certainly the implements were not attached and
therefore presumably the lamps themselves were not attached. אלא מה אני מקיים
את כל הכלים האלה Ela mah ani mekayem es kol hakelim ha-eleh
after it says you know this all from the כיכר Kikar and
and all these vessels, what does all these vessels mean? שהיו כלי
זהב. She-hayu klei zahav. That means that they're gold, but not that
they're from the כיכר Kikar and not that they're attached. So the
גמרא Gemara says זהב בהדיא כתיב בו, Zahav behedya kesiv bo, that's
explicit. ועשית את נרותיה שבעה והעלה את נרותיה והאיר אל עבר פניה
מלקחיה ומחתותיה זהב טהור. Ve-asisa es neroseha shivah ve-he-elah es neroseha ve-he-ir
el ever paneha melkacheha u-machtoseha zahav tahor. So
it's explicit that the various vessels and implements are gold. So what?
Not the נרות. Neros.
Not the נרות. Neros. Right. Ah, very good. So that's what the
גמרא Gemara is going to. לא נצרכה אלא לפי נרות. Lo nitzrecha
ela le-pi neros.
Only for the lips of the lamps themselves. סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka
da-atach amina,
I would have thought, הואיל ופי נרות השחור משחיר, Ho-il u-pi neros
hashachor mashchir,
since they become black because that's where the fire burns directly. And
therefore we have a principle that התורה חסה על ממונם של ישראל,
Ha-Torah chasah al mamonam shel Yisrael, the תורה Torah is concerned with
the money of the Jewish people, so ולא עבדי זהב כל דהו,
Ve-la avdi zahav kol dehu, make it some form of gold. רש"י
Rashi says it means a gold alloy, don't make it pure gold
because that would get destroyed if you burned right where the fire
was burning. So קא משמע לן, Ka mashma lan, therefore it has
to emphasize that although the תורה Torah is not explicit that the
lamps are of pure gold, they should be they are they are
also of pure gold.
So it always begs the question why not just state it outright
and not have to have another פסוק Pasuk to like... No, not
to have another
פסוק, Pasuk, that was just his assertion, we actually didn't learn it
from a פסוק, Pasuk, it was just his assertion that they were
of pure gold.
It says את כל הכלים האלה. Es kol hakelim ha-eleh. Right. ושיעורו
כלי זהב. Ve-shiurom klei zahav.
Oh, I'm sorry, you're right. The את כל הכלים, Es kol hakelim,
I'm sorry, you're correct. Correct.
So why another פסוק Pasuk if we could have had one word
over there?
I don't know, Michael, this is the משכן Mishkan
after
all, so
we're going to have to answer that, we'll have to answer a
lot of פסוקים. Psukim. Okay, anyway, so that's the end of the
מנורה Menorah discussion, but again, what is I think particularly interesting is
the question about you know about whether the lamps were physically connected
to allow for better cleaning. And also the issues we discussed yesterday
in particular, which is you know about how did they what did
they do if it first of all if it went out in
the middle of light night did they have to relight it? That
was one issue yesterday which was the simple read of the גמרא.
Gemara. And then the other thing we brought in yesterday which was
the רמב"ם's Rambam position, a very different read of the גמרא, Gemara,
which was against a lot of other גמרות Gemoros and all the
other ראשונים, Rishonim, but the רמב"ם Rambam understands that they relit it
every morning so that it was constantly burning, the מנורה, Menorah, and
that the cleaning and the relighting, we normally think the lighting occurred
at the night and the cleaning in the morning, the רמב"ם Rambam
actually says that both of those things always went together and they
did it twice a day, once at the beginning of night and
once first thing in the morning. Okay, so now we continue top
of פ"ט עמוד א'. Pey Tes Amud Aleph. חצי לוג שמן לתודה.
Chatzi log shemen le-todah. So what would you use the חצי לוג
Chatzi Log for? For the oil of a תודה. Todah. Now remember
the normal amount that goes with a מנחה Mincha is a לוג
Log for an עשרון. Isaron. A תודה Todah actually has a lot
more than an עשרון. Isaron. A תודה Todah has עשרה עשרונות Asarah
Esronos for the ten loaves of חמץ Chametz and עשרה עשרונות Asarah
Esronos for the thirty loaves of מצה. Matzah. So and now what
we are saying is this חצי לוג Chatzi Log by the way
is just for the מצה, Matzah, as we'll find out in a
minute, that that חצי לוג Chatzi Log is for thirty thirty עשרונות
Esronos of מצה. Matzah. So it's a much tinier proportion of oil,
right? Normally it's a לוג Log per עשרון, Isaron, it's like a
one to one ratio, and here it's a חצי לוג Chatzi Log
for for thirty, no, חצי לוג Chatzi Log for ten, excuse me,
thirty loaves, עשרה עשרונות. Asarah Esronos. So it's a one to twenty
ratio, much much less oil than normal. חצי לוג שמן לתודה. Chatzi
log shemen le-todah. דתניא Detanya we taught in a ברייתא, Baraita, רבי
עקיבא אומר, Rabbi Akiva omer, מה תלמוד לומר בשמן בשמן שני פעמים?
Mah talmud lomar ba-shemen ba-shemen shtei peamim? So the פסוק Pasuk says
here, רש"י Rashi quotes the פסוק, Pasuk, חלות מצות בלולות בשמן ורקיקי
מצות משוחים בשמן Chalos matzos belulos ba-shemen u-rekikei matzos meshuchim ba-shemen וסולת
מרבכת חלות Ve-soles murbaches chalos and then the end of the פסוק
Pasuk is what is it? וסולת מרבכת חלות. Ve-soles murbaches chalos. plus
בשמן bashemen three times by the three מצות matzot and we’re going
to interpret what that means. So why does it say בשמן bashemen
twice? אילו לא נאמר אלא בשמן אחד, Ilu lo ne’emar ela bashemen
echad, had it only said with oil once, הייתי אומר הרי הוא
ככל המנחות ללוג. hayiti omer harei hu kechol hamnachot lelog. It’s like
all the other מנחות menachot that it gets a לוג. log. Now
again, even that is ironic because or unusual because the normal מנחות
menachot as I said get a לוג log per עשרון issaron and
here it is עשרה עשרונות asara isronot as said by the תודה,
toda, thank you, עשרה עשרונות asara isronot and it's all getting just
one לוג. log. But however, do remember that in the משנה mishna
we did have the opinion of who was it that said that
no matter how big the מנחה mincha is it only gets one
לוג. log. רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov says you
could have a מנחה mincha of like 30 עשרונות isronot and it
gets one לוג. log. It's a לוג log per מנחה, mincha, not
per עשרון. issaron. But nevertheless, our general assumption is a לוג log
per עשרון issaron and here he said had it not said anything
special, I would have assumed like every other מנחה mincha a לוג.
log. But still, it's a לוג log for עשרה עשרונות. asara isronot.
Okay, anyway, that said it just said בשמן bashemen once. הרי הוא
ככל המנחות ללוג. Harei hu kechol hamnachot lelog. עכשיו שנאמר בשמן בשמן,
Achshav shene'emar bashemen bashemen, now it says בשמן bashemen twice, הוי ריבוי
אחר ריבוי. havei ribui achar ribui. It is a, you know,
inclusive expansive word after another expansive word. ואין ריבוי אחר ריבוי אלא
למעט. Ve'ein ribui achar ribui ela lema'et. And of course if it,
if you're going to doubly insist on how much oil it means,
it must mean that there's actually less oil. We're going to get
to the three times in a minute. First the גמרא Gemara has
a question why is it doubly insisting? So the גמרא Gemara says,
so let's finish this. מיעטו הכתוב לחצי לוג. Mi'ato hakatuv lechatzi log.
Half a לוג. log. Not a full לוג, log, but it's less
than that. What's less than a full? Is a half. יכול יהא
חצי לוג זה מתחלק לשלשה מינין לחלות ורקיקין ורביכה. Yachol yehei chatzi
log zeh mitchalek leshlosha minim lachalot urekikin urevicha. Maybe you take this
half לוג log and you divide it equally to the three types
of מצות matzot you have. Ten, you know, ten loaves of מצה
matza each. כשהוא אומר בשמן ברביכה. Keshehu omer bashemen barevicha. No, it
says a third בשמן, bashemen, right? It says חלות מצות בלולות בשמן
ורקיקי מצות משוחים בשמן וסולת מורבכת חלות בלולות בשמן. chalot matzot blulot
bashemen urekikei matzot meshuchim bashemen v'solet murbachet chalot blulot bashemen. So it
says בשמן bashemen again by the רביכה revicha by the, by the
what do you call it, by the רביכים revichim by the חלות
chalot that are רביכה revicha whichever that is, which is explicit by
the תודה toda in צו. Tzav.
Okay, so what is it, why does it say בשמן bashemen a
third time? שאין תלמוד לומר. She'ein talmud lomar.
There's no need to say שמן shemen a third time. So now
that we've already been ממעט mema'et by the second time it says
בשמן, bashemen, we'll use the third time it says בשמן bashemen to
go back and to be more, you know, more expansive. שריבה שמן
לרביכה. Sheriba shemen larevicha. So now it's saying that there's more oil
for the רביכים revichim than there is for the חלות chalot and
the רקיקין. rekikin. הא כיצד, Ha keitzad, how do you do this?
So you don't actually have more than the full half לוג, log,
but here's what you do. מביא חצי לוג שמן וחוציהו. Mevi chatzi
log shemen vechotzeihu. You take a half לוג log and you divide
it equally. חציו לחלות ורקיקין, chetzyo lachalot urekikin, half for the חלות
chalot and the
רקיקין, rekikin, וחציו לרביכה v’chetzyo larevicha for the רביכה. revicha. So again
it's a little bit what, what's a רביכה? revicha? Well that is
a good question. The גמרא Gemara actually although it describes the different
מנחות menachot never specifically describes this, but I believe the way רש״י
Rashi says it's like a more like a deep pan type of
a, yeah, I think so. I don't know, what, what's the book
for any metadata?
Yeah, does the book have pictures?
Yeah, let's see. Let's see about this רביכה. revicha.
What
do you say Mordy, do you know what a,
no good רשב״ם Rashbam on that?
This about this stuff it's all explained in מנחות. Menachot.
You can take a,
I don't know. It's okay. All right, whatever. It's a different way
it's made. It's obviously made with more oil as we see it
as twice as much oil. Now again, so what you have is
you have a quarter of a לוג. log. Remember, that's a רביעית.
revi'it. A רביעית revi'it is like, is like the smallest amount you
use for קידוש, kiddush, like three and a half ounces. So that
amount for all of the רביכה revicha of the, of the, you
know, things that are made רביכה revicha which is, which is חמשה
עשרונות. chamisha isronot. Again, an עשרון issaron is a five-pound bag of
flour, so we're talking about five five-pound bags of flour for a
little, for a little three ounces of oil. And then the others,
the חלות chalot and the רקיקין rekikin it's even less. It's the
same three ounces of oil but this is for the other, well
actually that was שלשה ושליש עשרון. shlosha v'shlish issaron. I'm sorry. Anyway,
so one more
time. You had the 30 חלות. chalot. Those 30 חלות chalot of
מצה matza were, you know, 10 of each חלות רקיקין ורביכה chalot
rekikin urevicha were made from עשרה עשרונות. asara isronot. Okay, so right,
so okay, ten עשרונות. isronot. So three and a third for each,
I guess, type. So anyway, so you had ששה ושני שלישי עשרונות
shisha v'shnei shlishi isronot for the חלות chalot and the רקיקין rekikin
which got a רביעית revi'it of oil which is again a like
three and a third ounces of oil. And then for what we're
saying is for the רביכה revicha which is another שלשה ושליש עשרון,
shlosha v'shlish issaron, three and a third five-pound bags of flour roughly,
you get another רביעית revi'it a tiny bit of oil. So here,
although you have more oil for the רביכה, revicha, proportionally it's still
very small related to, you know, the other מנחות menachot which was
basically a לוג log per עשרון. issaron. There, what did you want
to say?
רבוכין Revuchin is as though it was scalded in water and then
baked and then finally fried.
That's what I, oh, the
גמרא Gemara did say it already? Alright, I forgot.
That's also the דף daf that I gave it.
Oh, that's why I forgot. Very good. Alright.
Wait, wait, but
so I'm to understand what the גמרא Gemara is saying right now.
Right. So you have your 40 loaves, one of them gets a
half... Right. One of them gets a half a לוג. log. Yes.
No, no, no, you have 30 loaves. Your ten...
and your 40, aren't you? No, because ten are
חמץ. chametz.
Yes, but
the ten of חמץ, chametz, I believe gets their own separate half
לוג. log. Right. Of the 30 that are מצה, matzah, they get
a half לוג. log. Again, we're not talking about a lot here,
we're talking about like six ounces, okay, in ten עשרונות. isronos. Okay,
and of that, you divide it between the 30, but of that
you do a רביעית revi'is for 20 of the loaves and another
רביעית revi'is for the other ten. Okay. Alright. There we go. So
now moving on...
but which are which for which?
Yeah, well that is the question because it says בשמן bashemen three
times, so you only get more in the רבוכה revucha if you
interpret the פסוק pasuk sequentially, but we don't always interpret the פסוקים
pesukim sequentially, so I don't know. I don't know how we do
it. Okay.
That's the
position. אמר לו
רבי אלעזר בן עזריה:
Amar
lo
Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah: Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah said, עקיבא, Akiva, אם
אתה מרבה כל היום כולו בשמן בשמן איני שומע לך. im atah
marbeh kol hayom kulo bashemen bashemen eini someia lach. You can have
your בשמן bashemen as much as you want, that's not how we
know this stuff. This is sort of like my basic response every
time Michael asks me this question, which is how do you get
it out of that? That's what he says, רבי עקיבא, Rebbi Akiva,
you're not going to get it from the פסוק. pasuk. אלא, Ella,
here's how you're going to get it. חצי לוג שמן לתודה, Chatzi
log shemen l'sodah, the idea that you use a half of a
לוג log for the מצה matzah loaves of the תודה, todah, ורביעית
שמן לנזיר, u'revi'is shemen l'nazir, and the idea that you use a
רביעית revi'is of oil for the נזיר nazir and
for his מנחה, minchah, which was mentioned earlier in the משנה, mishnah,
ואחד עשר יום שבין נדה לנדה, v'achad asar yom she'bein niddah l'niddah,
that was an interesting thing to throw in, the 11 days between
נדה niddah cycles, I'll explain that in a minute, all of that
is הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai. That's just from tradition, like
many of the שיעורים, shiurim, you're not going to get it in
the פסוקים pesukim that you can know where you can figure it
out from the פסוקים. pesukim. Now, one of the reasons that by
the way that the רש"י Rashi says that the, I thought I
must have skipped a line in the גמרא, Gemara, no, because hold
on one minute. One minute.
One minute. One minute.
Yeah, I skipped a line in the גמרא. Gemara. I thought I
skipped something. If you go back way in the גמרא, Gemara, because
the גמרא Gemara actually clarifies that the, that there's a problem doing
ריבוי אחר ריבוי ribui achar ribui by the שמן shemen twice. If
you take a look back in the גמרא, Gemara, I don't know,
I must have skipped this. Anyway,
so if you take a look, one, two, three, four, five, I'm
sorry, one, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight,
nine, ten, ten lines from the top, last word of the line
where it says ריבוי, ribui, the line afterwards says אחר ריבוי. achar
ribui. So after רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva said ריבוי אחר ריבוי, ribui
achar ribui, right? It says בשמן bashemen twice, so it's coming to
actually be less, the גמרא Gemara actually asks on that. ריבוי אחר
ריבוי, Ribui achar ribui, says the גמרא, Gemara, ואין ריבוי אחר ריבוי
אלא למעט. v'ein ribui achar ribui ella l'ma'et. One minute. No, I
just read myself again. Somewhere the
גמרא Gemara asks on that,
I'm just going crazy. Hold on a minute. הרי ריבוי הוי ריבוי.
Harei ribui havei ribui. Oh, חד ריבויהו, chad ribuyu, I was right.
So the גמרא Gemara says
ריבוי אחר ריבוי, ribui achar ribui, חד ריבויהו, chad ribuyu, right? It's
not a double ריבוי. ribui. It says בשמן בשמן bashemen bashemen twice,
but the first time it was saying בשמן, bashemen, it was only
saying it for its own sake, that it needs oil. So it's
only one ריבוי, ribui, it's not a double ריבוי. ribui. The second
time it says בשמן bashemen is not a doubling, a double expansive.
The first בשמן bashemen was for its own sake, the second בשמן
bashemen was coming to say more, so it's only one more, it's
not two mores. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא, ella, rather, אילו
לא נאמר בשמן כל עיקר, ilu lo ne'emar bashemen kol ikkar, had
it not said בשמן bashemen at all, הייתי אומר הרי הוא ככל
המנחות, hayiti omer harei hu k'chol hamenachos, I wouldn't have even needed
בשמן bashemen to tell me that it gets oil. Of course it
gets oil, like all מנחות menachos get
oil, ולוג. v'log. אלא שנאמר בשמן בשמן, Ella she'ne'emar bashemen bashemen, so
it says בשמן bashemen twice, הוי ריבוי אחר ריבוי ואין ריבוי אחר
ריבוי אלא
למעט. havei ribui achar ribui v'ein ribui achar ribui ella l'ma'et. So
I somehow skipped those five lines. Okay. So anyway, do people see
where I went back to read there? From the top, basically the
גמרא Gemara was just bothered with a technical point, but I knew
it was there. Anyway, that saying בשמן bashemen twice is not a
double ריבוי. ribui. The first בשמן bashemen has to tell me that
you need oil, the second בשמן bashemen is a ריבוי. ribui. So
it says, no, no, no, it didn't even have to tell me
you needed oil. Had it just said it was a מנחה, minchah,
I would have assumed it needed oil. So the fact that it
tells me בשמן bashemen even once is already a ריבוי, ribui, and
telling me twice is ריבוי אחר ריבוי אלא למעט. ribui achar ribui
ella l'ma'et. The reason I just mentioned this is because רבי אלעזר
בן עזריה's Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah response to רבי עקיבא, Rebbi Akiva,
which is "Don't bother me with the בשמןs," bashemen I mean I
think we take this at the simple level, which is either like,
you know, there's no way you're really going to get it out
of the פסוק... pasuk... Okay, you know you might have extra בשמנים,
bashemens, but there’s no clear line to get from there to exactly
where you want to get, which is like a רביעית revi'it for
these loaves and a רביעית revi'it for those loaves and so on.
רש"י Rashi though says that what's bothering רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi
Elazar ben Azariah is the more technical point that the גמרא Gemara
said earlier, which is is that it's not two ריבויים, ribu'im, it's
only one ריבוי, ribui, and if it's only one ריבוי ribui you're
never going to get there. But it seems that his argument is
more fundamental and you do actually have this, this is like a
nice trope that the גמרא Gemara has a couple of times, not
always the same תנא tanna interestingly saying this to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi
Akiva, but רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is almost always the one that's
being said to. So it's
sometimes it's רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, sometimes it's I forget who it
is, but it's somebody, but it's always saying רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva,
you can go with your extra ווים vavs as much as you
want or your extra בשמנים bashemens as much as you want, you're
never going to really get to where you're trying to go because
רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, if you remember, he was the one according
to the גמרא Gemara that was דורש doresh the קוצו של יוד.
kotzo shel yud. He felt that you could get anything you wanted
from the tiny little nuances in the text and not all the
תנאים tanna'im agreed with him. Sometimes they felt they might have agreed
with his ruling but felt that you have to sort of start
with an assumption that that's the הלכה, halacha, maybe it's הלכה למשה
מסיני halacha l'Moshe mi-Sinai or maybe you learn it elsewhere but you're
not going to be able to get everything just by hermeneutics applied
to the text. I think what's particularly fascinating
is that it's always this is the constant critique of רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva but it's not always the same תנא tanna who's issuing
the critique. Now the idea of the י"א יום, yud alef yom,
so two of the things are mentioned in our משנה, mishnah, the
half of the לוג log of oil for the תודה todah which
we said is for the thirty loaves, which is a very tiny
amount of oil for the תודה, todah, and the רביעית revi'it of
oil for the נזיר nazir which is also a much smaller amount
than normally goes with a מנחה. mincha. A מנחה mincha is normally
a full לוג, log, this is a quarter of a לוג. log.
But anyway those are cases in our משנה, mishnah, that's the מנחה.
mincha. What's the י"א יום בין נדה לנדה? yud alef yom bein
niddah l'niddah? We're going to see this soon enough when we get
to נדה, niddah, but just to explain it to you that basically
according to the תורה, Torah, when a woman bleeds during her menstrual
cycle she's a נדה niddah and there's seven days in which she's
טמאה temeiah and then she goes to the מקווה mikvah and she
can go to the מקווה mikvah even if she was bleeding the
entire seven days. If she bleeds not during her menstrual cycle, בלא
עת נדתה, b'lo eit niddatah, so if it's once or twice then
she needs just one clean day and then she goes to the
מקווה, mikvah, but if it's three days in a row בלא עת
נדתה, b'lo eit niddatah, not during her normal period, then she is
considered a זבה zavah and it's seven clean days before she goes
to the מקווה. mikvah. We somehow have conflated the two, we'll discuss
that when we learn מסכת נדה. masechet niddah. So what is that
period which is considered not during her menstrual cycle, בלא עת נדתה,
b'lo eit niddatah, that she can become a זבה? zavah? So we
basically say from the onset of her menstruation, then she a woman
menstruates, she becomes a נדה, niddah, seven days, she goes to the
מקווה. mikvah. After that seven days is over, after she basically has
gone to the מקווה, mikvah, now there's an eleven day period, י"א
יום. yud alef yom. During those eleven days, if she bleeds it's
considered to be bleeding not during her menstrual period. Anytime she bleeds
after those eleven days, it's considered to be a possible menstruation, which
basically means the גמרא's Gemara saying, this הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'Moshe
mi-Sinai saying, that we can assume a menstrual cycle as short as
eighteen days. So anytime the next bleeding occurs eighteen days out from
the first bleeding we'll assume that it's another menstruation. But if it's
within that eleven day period after seven days from the onset and
then that eleven days, then it's obviously something that’s not menstrual bleeding
and that's when a woman could become a זבה. zavah. So that's
the י"א יום. yud alef yom. He says none of this stuff
you're going to get from the פסוקים, pesukim, this stuff can only
be a הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha l'Moshe mi-Sinai. You will not be
surprised to find out that there is a ספרא Sifra that tries
to get this from the פסוקים, pesukim, the י"א יום. yud alef
yom. But we'll worry about that when we get to מסכת נדה.
masechet niddah. Okay now we go on. Okay בלוג היה מודד, B'log
hayah moded, so now the משנה mishnah went on to say that
you would always measure with a לוג, log, even if you had
a מנחה mincha of sixty עשרונות, isronot, you would not use a
bigger measure, you would take the לוג log and measure it out
sixty times, although you did have bigger liquid measures, but as I
pointed out you actually when it came to the solid
measures, we said you only had an עשרון. issaron. So if you
dedicated a מנחה mincha of sixty עשרונות, isronot, you're going to have
to measure it out with an עשרון issaron sixty times, so don't
use a bigger liquid measure, measure out the liquid, the שמן, shemen,
with a לוג log sixty times. That's what the משנה mishnah said.
תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, so we taught: במצורע עני כתיב, B'metzora ani
ktiv, it says by the מצורע עני, metzora ani, עשרון סולת בלול
בשמן ולוג שמן. issaron solet balul bashemen v'log shamen. So what does
it say actually? Thank you, I'll take the פסוק. pasuk. So what
does it say by the מצורע? metzora? This is actually interesting, we
use what the תורה Torah says about the מצורע metzora to be
the paradigm for all מנחות menachot that you have a לוג log
per עשרון. issaron. So when the מצורע metzora discusses the מצורע metzora
and how he becomes pure and it discusses a normal מצורע metzora
brings three sheep, but if the מצורע metzora is poor, he only
brings one sheep and he brings a מנחה. mincha. And what does
that מנחה mincha consist of? So here's what the תורה Torah says:
ואם דל הוא ואין ידו משגת, v'im dal hu v'ein yado maseget,
so he's poor, ולקח כבש אחד
אשם
לתנופה
לכפר עליו,
v'lakach keves echad asham
litnufah l'chaper alav, he takes one lamb for an אשם, asham, ועשרון
סולת אחד בלול בשמן v'issaron solet echad balul bashemen and one עשרון
issaron of flour balul. בשמן bashamen mixed with oil, למנחה ולג שמן
l'mincha v'log shamen for a מנחה mincha and a לג log of
oil. Now this לג שמן log shamen actually is not what he
is mixing his מנחה mincha with, his לג log of oil is
actually what he is using for the מצורע metzora for this whole
ritual on his ears and so on. But because it says ולג
שמן v'log shamen we are going to use this פסוק pasuk to
tell us that that is the amount of oil you mix per
עשרון issaron of מנחה. mincha. So it's not at all פשט pshat
but that is what we're going to learn from it. במצורע עני
כתיב עשרון בלול ולוג. B'metzora ani kesiv issaron balul v'log. לימד על
עשרון שטעון לוג. Limed al issaron shetoun log. So it says an
עשרון issaron and a לג, log, so the ratio is one לג
log per עשרון. issaron. דברי חכמים. Divrei chachamim. That is what the
חכמים chachamim say. רבי נחמיה ורבי אליעזר אומרים Rebbi Nechemia v'Rebbi Eliezer
omrim no, אפילו מנחה של ששים עשרונים afilu mincha she'shishim esronim even
if it's 60 עשרונות esronos which is the maximum size per מנחה,
mincha, אין לה אלא לוגה. ein lah ela logah. There is only
one לג log per מנחה mincha no matter how much flour you
have. שנאמר she'ne'emar again remember they added water so they were able
to turn it into dough even if it didn't have a lot
of
oil. שנאמר she'ne'emar למנחה ולוג שמן. l'mincha v'log shamen. Don't read it
עשרון ולוג, issaron v'log, read it למנחה ולוג. l'mincha v'log. No matter
how big your מנחה mincha is, it's only one לג. log. ורבי
נחמיה ורבי אליעזר האי עשרון בלול ולוג מאי עביד ליה? V'Rebbi Nechemia
v'Rebbi Eliezer hai issaron balul v'log mai avid lei? What do they
do with what do they do with the fact that it mentions
an עשרון? issaron? So maybe that עשרון issaron is telling you a
לג log per עשרון? issaron? So the גמרא Gemara says no, ההוא
לגופיה. hahu l'gufia. That you need it to tell you the very
law itself דקאמר רחמנא ליתי חד עשרון d'ka'amar rachamana leisei chad issaron
that a מצורע metzora brings a מנחה mincha of one עשרון. issaron.
It is not telling you עשרון issaron and לג, log, it is
not coming to tell you our thing, it is coming to tell
you the פסוק pasuk about the מצורע metzora that the מצורע metzora
brings a מנחה mincha that is an
עשרון. issaron. Okay ואידך v'idach what would the response back be? לגופיה
לא צריך. L'gufia lo tzarich. The תורה Torah didn't have to tell
you how much flour to use for this מצורע. metzora. Why not?
מדגלי רחמנא
גבי מצורע ג' קרבנות וג' עשרונות Midegali rachamana gabei metzora gimmel korbanos
v'gimmel esronos when it talks about the מצורע metzora that's rich that's
not rich whatever not poor that brings the three the three animals
the three sheep and there it says and he brings a מנחה
mincha of three עשרונות. esronos. So therefore I could say I would
have made an analogy. הכא דחד קרבן. Hacha d'chad korban. So basically
what the תורה Torah says is a מצורע metzora brings three things,
an אשם asham and a חטאת chatas and an עולה. olah. Now
if he's if he's not poor all of those come from sheep.
If he is poor the אשם asham is the key for the
מצורע metzora that really does the טהרה tahara process. So that has
to remain the sheep and he is able to replace the חטאת
chatas and the עולה olah instead of these two sheep with a
with two birds, one for a חטאת chatas and one for an
עולה. olah. So there and what else the תורה Torah said is
when it said spoke about the non-poor מצורע metzora it said he
brings these three sheep and a מנחה mincha of three עשרונות. esronos.
Well this also לג שמן log shamen I know
well that לג log right but we're bracketing the לג log now
we're talking about לגופיה l'gufia what I would have thought for the
מנחה. mincha. Okay so when he brings the three sheep it says
he brings a מנחה mincha of three so here he's bringing one
sheep and he's the other things are birds so I would have
said by analogy I would have realized that if the if the
animals are switching from a three to one ratio, right so here
too the מנחה mincha would switch from a three to one ratio
and it would have been one. And if so the תורה Torah
didn't have to say עשרון. issaron. Why does it say
עשרון? issaron? To link עשרון issaron to a לג log and to
tell me it always has that ratio. ואידך V'idach what's the response
back? איצטריך. Itzterich. No the תורה Torah had to tell you here
עשרון. issaron. Why? סלקא דעתך אמינא Salka da'atach amina I would have
thought הואיל וחס רחמנא עליה hoil v'chas rachamana alei since the תורה
Torah is being you know compassionate on you helping you save money
this poor מצורע metzora לאתויי בדלות l'asuyei b'dalus
and you can bring in a lower economic level of your you
know קרבן korban you can bring with a less expensive קרבן korban
and you only have to bring one sheep אימא לא ליבעי מיניה
כלל eima lo libei minei klal maybe you wouldn't have to bring
a מנחה mincha at all. Maybe you know the same way it
got you off of it replaced the the two you know the
two sheep with two birds maybe it would have gotten you off
of the מנחה mincha altogether.
I don't see that anyway.
ואידך V'idach and that is of course a bizarre point because why
does it just say מנחה mincha the real point is it didn't
have to say the word עשרון issaron I could have figured out
the עשרון. issaron. Okay but anyway so that is the response back.
לגמרי לא אשכחן. Legamrei lo ashkan. No we never would have found
that the תורה Torah was doing away with it. In all of
the cases the תורה Torah is creating a substitute. The תורה Torah
says instead of two sheep for an עולה olah and חטאת chatas
bring two birds for an עולה olah and a חטאת. chatas. So
therefore we've always found a substitute, we've never found that it got
went away for it. All right so that's the argument. The argument
is the תורה Torah did not have to say עשרון issaron here
I could have figured it out by the ratio and therefore if
it says עשרון issaron it's to tell me this to tell me
that it's constantly this is the ratio of an עשרון issaron to
a לג. log. So can I? Yes go ahead what's your question?
See the problem is it depends which way you look at it
because if you look at the poor מצורע metzora then it says
you're right עשרון בלול ולוג issaron balul v'log right? That means every
עשרון issaron needs one לג log but if you look at it
for the first
part.
So that's a good point, but partly I would say the answer
is what we just said here, which is there you would say
it's צריך לגופיה. tzrich legufei. It has to tell you three עשרונות.
isronot. Here the argument is being made it didn't have to tell
you עשרון. issaron. So the fact that it repeats עשרון issaron is
to specifically link an עשרון issaron to a לוג. log. So that's
presumably the logic.
So then you can say that for the rich one, since he's
bringing so many, okay now we're gonna כאפן chappen that and have
this even more... let me just do one more for all three.
No, but the לוג log there is again this is a דרשה.
drasha. The לוג log there is not the amount of oil that
went into the מנחה. mincha. The לוג log there is to use
for the ritual of the מצורע.
metzora. Right, but you can have דרשה drasha here.
I know, but I'm saying because here the argument is that it's
extra. Okay, but you're right. Again, Michael, I would say to you
what whoever said Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah said back to Rabbi Akiva.
None of these דרשות drashot really bother me, alright? I assume that
חז"ל Chazal in most of these cases, not in all cases, but
in most of these cases, started with that they knew where they
were going. Alright, so anyway.
Alright, so now let me get back to them then.
You know, half of those דרשות drashot don't make sense either. Well,
let me just tell you this, which is like a middle position
because it actually is an interesting debate by both of scholars and
the ראשונים Rishonim in general this question about דרשות. drashot. Do you
start with assuming that they knew what the law was and the
דרשה drasha was there for some type of like an אסמכתא? asmachta?
Or do you start that they assume they didn't know what the
law was and they actually derived it from the דרשה? drasha? So
that's, you know, so obviously the answer probably is somewhere in the
middle. Like sometimes you really get a sense that they are trying
to figure out the law from the פסוקים psukim and sometimes you
get a sense like they knew it and they were just working
backwards. The רמב"ם Rambam actually already raised this question, this is not
just an academic issue, and he comes up with an interesting פשרה
peshara because the רמב"ם Rambam is bothered, it's a little digression but
I might as well say it, the רמב"ם Rambam is bothered that
you know the גמרא Gemara says that you need a מסורה messorah
for גזירה שוה. gezeirah shavah. You don't because a גזירה שוה gezeirah
shavah obviously you could learn whatever the heck you wanted just as
it says ויאמר vayomer here and ויאמר vayomer there. So the גמרא
Gemara says you need a מסורה messorah for גזירה שוה. gezeirah shavah.
So the רמב"ם Rambam says, okay but how come the גמרא Gemara
then says questions like, well, why learn a גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah
this way, why not learn a גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah that way?
What type of question is that if you need a מסורה messorah
for גזירה שוה? gezeirah shavah? So the רמב"ם Rambam says, what we
must really say is is that it's not a מסורה messorah of
the specific גזירה שוה. gezeirah shavah. You like have a מסורה messorah
that you can learn the law through a גזירה שוה, gezeirah shavah,
but you're still free to figure out how to make the גזירה.
gezeirah. But the point being that there is some position between אסמכתא
asmachta and real derivation. It could very well be that חז"ל Chazal
sort of knew that this was the הלכה halacha and they knew
that there was a way to derive it from the פסוקים psukim
or they believed that it could be derived from the פסוקים. psukim.
So they're not just doing their דרשות drashot as a type of
an אסמכתא, asmachta, but at the but they still know where they
have to get. Okay, they still sort of know this is the
end point and somehow we can derive it from the פסוקים. psukim.
And I think that that's a lot of the times what you
have to assume. Now when there's a real מחלוקת machlokes about the
הלכה halacha and the מחלוקת machlokes is because one person learns the
פסוק pasuk this way and the other that way, that's where you
get a sense
that maybe they really are debating, you know, the actual derivation they
really are deriving the law. But that's always the question. In case
of something similar. Yes. The whole idea of the development of the
מסורה messorah or the
how it played out over time is that originally it was on
מסורה. messorah. Right. And as the מסורה messorah becomes forgotten, the rules
come into play. Right.
And then you have to reconstitute it. Right. But of course what
that that makes all the enterprise of תורה שבעל פה Torah SheBaal
Peh just one of reconstruction and not one of creativity.
Well, he doesn't deny that there is such a thing as, well,
no on the contrary, it changed once
once it's lost so you're not just reconstructing, then you're also deriving
afresh. Right. Anyway, if you want to see an interesting book on
this, Jay Harris has a book called How Do We Know This?
I think How Do We Know This? How Do We Know This?
Excellent book. And I'm just going to say one last digression then
we have to get back, which is he makes an excellent point
which is and it's a similar point David Berger made in a
different context about justifying the actions of the אבות Avot in the
פסוקים psukim that that how the Jewish scholars respond you know which
approach they took was an effect of where the critique was coming
from. That when there was a time where everybody was sort of
like saying like, you know, how does it work? He says that
you know sometimes the דרשות drashot seem crazy, right? So he says
so when people, what was it, it was like when people
were saying
when the critique was
that, he starts by saying like first, you know, everybody was insisting,
oh no no no it's all מסיני. MiSinai. Oh, I guess I
guess that what was it?
I guess that's against the צדוקים Tzaddukim when everyone...
I'm trying to remember how it works but somehow like when everybody
when the question was
was like yeah you don't really believe in תורה שבעל פה, Torah
SheBaal Peh, it's all מסיני. MiSinai. Then you insist, no no no
these דרשות drashot are really real and we're really getting it and
so on. And then when when it was what was being critiqued
was not the you know was like was the דרשות drashot themselves
and basically it was like this is so silly and how do
you expect us to believe in this enterprise of you know of
these דרשות, drashot, you know, you're making all these crazy... these things
and says no no no the דרשות drashot are not really real
we really already knew the הלכה halakha we're really just going back
and like it's really an אסמכתא asmakhta and so on so he
I forget exactly the details but he basically points out how which
approach was sort of taken by the sort of frum Jewish scholars
to say whether the דרשות drashot were real or not was depending
like you know which sort of where they were being critiqued from
and what they had to respond David Berger makes the same point
about when the the the
ethical actions or the questionable actions of the אבות avot in the
פסוקים psukim that when everybody believed that the תורה Torah was from
God and therefore the Christians were critiquing look you Jews you're terrible
look at what יעקב Yaakov has done and you know whatever you
don't have good morals says no no you have to understand what
he was dealing was really righteous you know and explains how the
whole thing you know what to to justify his actions but then
when the what was really was a question was was whether the
תורה Torah was from God or not so then the point was
how can you say the תורה Torah is from God if the
תורה Torah holds up יעקב Yaakov as an example but says no
you don't understand יעקב Yaakov was really punished for his sins as
he's not being held up as an example so exactly you know
how what's defended is as a function of what's being critiqued
anyway then there's the basic question of why this extra לוג log
is mentioned here specifically by the מצורע metzora
you're back to that
every מנחה mincha is like by the regular מנחה mincha you know
okay anyway do you
have another answer for that I no
I don't
know okay so now the גמרא Gemara says like this let's go
on
okay where were we ואידך ve-idach okay so ג' קבין ד' ג'
סלת אחת חמשיה gimel kabin daled gimel solet achat chamisha ואידך איצטריך
סלקא דעתך אמינא ve-idach itztrich salka daitach amina so
here's the one that says no it's not a ratio of a
לוג log to an עישרון issaron it's a לוג log for every
מנחה mincha I need it I might have thought הואיל וחס רחמנא
עליה לאתויי בדלות hoil ve-chas rachmana alei le-aituyei be-dalus אימא לא בעי
מיניה כלל eima lo bei minei klal
oh I guess I did that already okay לגבי לוג legabei log
okay ורבנן האי למנחה ולוג שמע מינה מאי
עבדי ליה ve-rabbanan hai le-mincha ve-log shma mina mai avdi lei what
do the rabbis do with the juxtaposition of למנחה ולוג le-mincha ve-log
which says that it seems to be a לוג log for every
מנחה mincha no matter how big ההוא למתנדב מנחה שלא יפחות מדבר
הטעון לוג hahu le-misnadeiv mincha she-lo yifchos mi-davar ha-taun log
that tells you when you donate a מנחה mincha it can't be
less than an עישרון issaron a מנחה mincha has to always be
what something that demands a לוג log meaning it always has to
be at least an עישרון issaron of flour you can't have a
half of an עישרון issaron ומאי ניהו עישרון u-mai nihu issaron ואידך
ve-idach
what would the other one say back תרתי שמעת מינה tarti shmat
mina no if it says every מנחה mincha gets a לוג log
and it also says I don't know you know that this was
an עישרון issaron so we learn from that that a מנחה mincha
is minimally an עישרון issaron but also it's always one לוג log
per מנחה mincha so it's actually quite fascinating as Michael points out
and the real answer I would say Michael is is that the
תורה Torah itself and the פשט pshat of the פסוקים psukim do
not have a שיעור shiur for how much oil they just say
you mix it with oil they don't have a שיעור shiur right
so therefore if we're going to try to find a שיעור shiur
we get it from this one case of a מצורע metzora where
the שיעור shiur of the oil is not really for the מנחה
mincha but it's really for the separate לוג log of oil used
for the מצורע metzora ritual but because of the juxtaposition that allows
us now to create a שיעור shiur to identify a שיעור shiur
you know for the מנחה mincha and then the question is is
it a לוג log for the עישרון issaron or is it a
לוג log for or is it a לוג log for the מנחה
mincha no matter how big okay so now we go on ששה
לפר ארבעה לאיל שלשה לכבש shisha le-par arba'a le-ayil shlosha le-keves that's
the amount that you have for the לוגים logim because there's twelve
לוג log for a הין hin so half a הין hin for
a פר par is six a third for an איל ayil is
four a quarter for a כבש keves is three מנלן manlan how
do you know that there are twelve לוג log for a הין
hin which is a funny question דכתיב de-chsiv the פסוק pasuk says
ונסכם חצי ההין יהיה לפר ve-niskeichem chatzi ha-hin yihye le-par so half
a הין hin הני תריסר לוגי הויין hani treisar logei havyan and
a הין hin is twelve לוג log דכתיב de-chsiv now how do
you know a הין hin is twelve לוג log שמן זית הין
shemen zayit hin okay that the oil they used for the שמן
המשחה shemen ha-mishcha was a הין hin וכתיב u-chsiv another פסוק pasuk
says שמן משחת קודש יהיה זה לי לדורותיכם shemen mishchas kodesh yihye
zeh li le-doroseichem this will be the holy oil of anointing זה
zeh בגימטריא תריסר הוי be-gimatria treisar havei right so זה zeh is
twelve so that's how we know of course there are twelve לוג
log so obviously the question is who needs a פסוק pasuk to
tell you you know your ratio of measures either you know what
the ratio is or you don't but anyway but the point is
both measures are mentioned in the תורה Torah the תורה Torah says
a לוג log the תורה Torah speaks about a הין hin the
תורה Torah never tells you the conversion factor so rather than just
saying we happen to know it by tradition again we're linking it
but one does presume that this is really an אסמכתא asmakhta
okay so therefore שלשה ומחצה למנורה חצי לוג לכל נר shlosha u-mechtza
le-menora chatzi log le-chol ner three and a half לוג log for
מנורה menora half a לוג log for every candle so for every
lamp מנא הני מילי mana hanei milei where'd you know this from
תנו רבנן tanu rabbanan מערב עד בוקר me-erev ad boker you should
light it from evening through the morning תן לה מידתה שתהא דולקת
והולכת מערב עד בוקר ten lah midasah she-te-hei dolekes ve-holeches me-erev ad
boker it has to be enough oil that it can burn through
the night דבר אחר davar acher another way of reading it מערב
עד בוקר me-erev ad boker אין לך עבודה שכשירה מערב עד בוקר
אלא זו בלבד ein lecha avoda she-ksheira me-erev ad boker ela zu
bilvad the only עבודה avoda that is done in the only in
the evening is this תוספות Tosafot says what about the burning of
the fats says well that starts the day before what about the
תרומת הדשן trumas ha-deshen that's only towards the end of the evening
but the only עבודה avoda that goes through the night from the
beginning to the end is the lighting of the מנורה menora okay
אלא זו בלבד ela zu bilvad ושיערו חכמים חצי
לוג מאורתא ועד צפרא
ve-shiaru
chachamim chatzi
log me-orta ve-ad tzafra and the rabbis estimated half a לוג log
from evening until morning. Estimated that it would take a half of
a
לוג Log to go from the beginning of the evening through the
next morning. So איכא דאמרי, Ika De'amri, it's basically the same דרשה.
Drasha. איכא דאמרי מלמעלה למטה שיערו, Ika De'amri Milamala Lemata Shiuru, ואיכא
דאמרי מלמטה למעלה שיערו. v'ika de'amri milamata lemala shiuru. So here's the
interesting thing: we're actually talking about how they experimented until they got
the right amount. So some say they started taking a large amount
and then they kept on cutting it down until they took a
large amount, it went through to the next morning or two hours
into the morning. They cut it down a little and they kept
on cutting it down till they got it to go just through
the night, or the long nights
of the winter.
And some say the opposite: they started with underestimating, like a smaller
amount, and then they kept on adding till they got the amount
that they needed to go through. So what's the difference? מאן דאמר
מלמטה למעלה שיערו, Man De'amar Milamata Lemala Shiuru, that they started with
a small amount and they added: התורה חסה על ממונן של ישראל.
Hatorah Chasa Al Mamonan Shel Yisrael. They didn't want to waste the
oil because since the oil was sanctified in a כלי שרת, Kli
Shares, if it was extra and they didn't need it, they would
have to throw it out. So therefore, they wanted to use, they
started with a little less than they needed rather than a little
more than they needed. ומאן דאמר מלמעלה למטה שיערו, U'man De'amar Milamala
Lemata Shiuru, the one that says that they started with more and
they worked their way down: אין עניות במקום עשירות. Ein Aniyus Bemakom
Ashirus. You do not want to act like a sign of poverty
in a place that's supposed to be of wealth and of blessing,
and therefore you don't want to be stingy in the בית המקדש,
Beis Hamikdash, "Oh, let's only do this amount, maybe we'll get by
with this amount." You want to be expressing the idea of having
plenty and you're not focusing on doing it so exactly, and therefore
you do more and you work your way down. It's funny, right?
There's a שיעור Shiur for everything, and even for that, how much
oil to use for the night. Right. Yeah, so because there we
have a tradition that it says שיעור חכמים. Shiur Chachamim. Now, if
you look, there's a little תוספות Tosafot here, where תוספות Tosafot says,
ושיעור חכמים מאורתא ועד צפרא. V'shiur Chachamim Me'orta Ve'ad Tzafra. So תוספות
Tosafot says, ואם משתייר מן השמן בתקופת תמוז לא חיישינן, v'im mishtayer
min hashemen betkufas tammuz lo chaishinan, and if there was oil left
over in the summer because the nights are short, okay, so there's
oil left over. And then he says, ובירושלמי אמרינן דבימות החמה היו
עושים פתילה גסה, U'v'yerushalmi amrinan d'biyemos hachama hayu osim ptila gasa, right,
that's what I said yesterday, right, right, now I'm remembering that it
was in the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, so that in the summer they made
thicker wicks, ובימות החורף פתילה דקה, u'viyemos hachoref ptila daka, in the
winter thinner wicks. Okay, but nevertheless they estimated the amount of oil
for an average-sized wick. But when you had a shorter night, you
used a thicker wick so that it would burn till it would
not burn into the next day. Now there's another little short תוספות
Tosafot that has a great question, and I'll just read it to
you. It's this תוספות Tosafot about חצי לוג לכל נר ונר. Chatzi
Log Lechol Ner Vaner. תוספות Tosafot says, תימה למה, Teima Lama, you
see that תוספות? Tosafot? למה היה צריך לקדש השמן בכלי שרת? Lama
haya tzarich lekadesh hashemen bikli shares? We are assuming, right, the גמרא
Gemara is assuming that all of these measuring vessels were not just
measuring vessels, they were כלי שרת. Kli Shares. The גמרא Gemara already
assumed it before. Actually the גמרא Gemara said the only reason you
needed a half לוג Log as a כלי שרת Kli Shares was
specifically for the מנורה Menorah oil. So תוספות Tosafot says, why did
you need a כלי שרת? Kli Shares? Now what's his question? His
question is that normally you need a כלי שרת Kli Shares when
the object that you are sanctifying is a קרבן, Korban, is something
that is being offered. So you offer the flour, you offer the
wine, you offer the מנחה. Mincha. But he says you're not offering
the oil and burning it on the מנורה Menorah as an offering.
You're lighting the מנורה, Menorah, you're using, so your goal is to
achieve the light, not to actually offer a certain amount of oil.
The proof being that you can have less, this is also your
answer about the שיעור. Shiur. If it's a type of an offering,
you want to ensure how much of the thing do I need
to offer, right? But by the מנורה, Menorah, you just need it
to burn. So if it's a short night, you put up less.
If it's חנוכה, Chanukah, you can have a little bit that lasts
for a long time. But the point is you're not offering a
quantity of thing, you're just trying to light the מנורה. Menorah. So
he says, who needs you to be מקדש Mekadesh it in a
כלי שרת? Kli Shares? Which is a very interesting question. Now you
could try to argue that no, you do still need it if
you're using it in this type of service in the בית המקדש,
Beis Hamikdash, it still needs to be sanctified. But it's a great
question because it focuses us on the way in which the oil
is different. Some people want to say, for example, talking about חנוכה,
Chanukah, that you know the classic question: why don't we say טומאה
הותרה בציבור? Tumah Hutra B'tzibur? Why did they need to find the
פך שמן, Pach Shemen, it was טהור, Tahor, why didn't you just
say it's טמא Tamei and you can override? Is that well that
normally applies to a קרבן, Korban, that you can offer something בטומאה.
Betumah. But is the מנורה Menorah really a קרבן? Korban? It's an
עבודה Avoda that you do הדלקת המנורה, Hadlakas Hamenorah, but it's not
like a קרבן. Korban. So you know, maybe that doesn't have the
same rules as being overridden. So I think that's a very tiny
little תוספות Tosafot that focuses us on the way in which the
מנורה Menorah is different from other types of things. Okay, now we
move on to the next משנה. Mishna.
Doesn't that suggest that maybe it's the same?
I'm sorry? One more time?
Isn't that suggesting that the מנורה Menorah is a type of קרבן?
Korban?
When he's asking why does it need a כלי שרת? Kli Shares?
No, if it is then it would be obvious why it needs
a כלי שרת Kli Shares the same reason a מנחה Mincha needs
a כלי שרת. Kli Shares. The fact that he's saying why suggests
that he's assuming it's different, right, because everything needs a כלי שרת.
Kli Shares. I mean, you know, it's great that he asks the
question because normally you don't ask a question until there's like some
textual problem, but it just shows that his fundamental orientation to the
oil of the מנורה Menorah is different than it is towards everything
else. The מנורה Menorah needs a כלי שרת. Kli Sharei. The same
reason a מנחה Mincha needs a כלי שרת. Kli Sharei. The fact
that he's saying why suggests that he's assuming it's different, right? Because
everything needs a כלי שרת. Kli Sharei. It's great that he asks
the question because normally you don't ask the question unless there's like
some text or a problem. It just shows that his fundamental orientation
to the oil of the מנורה Menorah is different than it is
towards everything else. Okay, so now, מערבין נסכי פר עם נסכי אילים
ונסכי כבשים עם נסכי כבשים. Me'arvin nichsei par im nichsei elim u'nichsei
kvasim im nichsei kvasim. So here, although it says here נסכי, Nichsei,
which means the
libations, which suggest the wine, it really means the מנחה Mincha that
comes with the נסכים. Nisachim. Now let's talk about what the ratio
is. We've already had
this from previous משניות. Mishnayot. So the תורה Torah says שלושה עשרונים
לפר Shlosha esronim lapahr in terms of the flour, ושני עשרונים לאיל,
Ushnei esronim la'ayil, ועשרון לכבש. V'isaron lakeves. Three, two, one in terms
of the flour. What does it say about the oil and the
wine? So it says by the wine and we assume that the
oil is the same. So by the wine it says חצי ההין
לפר, Chatzi ha'hin lapahr, which is six לוג, Log, ושלישית ההין לאיל,
U'shlishit ha'hin la'ayil, which is three... I skipped it. ושלישית ההין לאיל
ורביעית ההין לכבש. U'shlishit ha'hin la'ayil u'revi'it ha'hin lakeves.
So it's six, four, three in terms of the wine and we
assume the same... we're going to see in the גמרא, Gemara, and
we assume the same in terms of the oil. So here it
is: three, two, one flour, six, four, three in terms of the
לוג. Log. So if you think about it, three and six is
a two to one ratio, right? Two... right, do you see this?
3-2-1 of the
עשרונות, Esronot, 6-4-3 in terms of the לוג. Log.
So three and six is a two to one. Two to four
is a two to one. But one to three is a three
to one. So the כבש Keves is a looser מנחה; Mincha; there's
more liquidy מנחה Mincha than the others. So the point of that
is... okay,
so the point of that is is that if you mix up...
what if you mix up the מנחות Minchot of one with the
other? So if you happen to dump together your מנחה Mincha for
your cow and your one for your ram, you have not changed
the distribution of the oil, the proportion of the oil, so that's
okay, you can just put it all on the מזבח Mizbeach even
if they got mixed up, fell in the same vessel. But if
the one of the lamb got mixed up with one of the
ram's or the cow, the oil proportion is different so it switches
the oil proportion of each one, it makes one too liquidy and
the other too, whatever, floury. So that's the problem. So that's what
our משנה Mishnah said. מערבין נסכי פר בנסכי אילים, Me'arvin nis'chei par
benis'chei elim, you can mix up the מנחות Minchot from the oxen
with the rams. נסכי כבשים בנסכי כבשים Nis'chei kvasim benis'chei kvasim of
the lambs with other lambs. של יחיד ושל ציבור, Shel yachid v'shel
tzibur, it doesn't matter if it's a private מנחה, Mincha, a private
קרבן Korban or a public קרבן. Korban. של יום ושל אמש, Shel
yom v'shel emesh, today's with yesterday's. Now not that you sanctified yesterday's
in a כלי שרת, Kli Sharei, then it would be פסול בלינה,
Pasul bilina, but you can bring the מנחה Mincha that comes with
the... right, מנחתם ונסכיהם אפילו מכאן ועד עשרה ימים. Minchatam v'nis'cheihem afilu
mikan v'ad asara yamim. You can bring it later. So if I
forgot to bring yesterday's מנחה Mincha with the קרבן Korban and I'm
bringing it today, I can mix up the מנחה Mincha with today's
קרבן Korban as long as the proportion of flour to oil is
the same. It's the same type of מנחה Mincha I'm mixing up.
אבל אין מערבין נסכי כבשים בנסכי פרים ואילים. Aval ein me'arvin nis'chei
kvasim benis'chei parim v'eilim. You cannot mix... the one thing you cannot
do is the lambs with the oxen and the rams because those
the proportions are different. ואם בללם אלו בפני עצמן ואלו בפני עצמן.
V'im b'lalam elu bifnei atzman v'elu bifnei atzman. Now if you already
had mixed the dough with the oil and I've now created my
oily dough for my ram and my more oily dough for my
lambs. So you've already done the mixing separately and now what happens?
ונתערבו, V'nitarvu, and then they got mixed up. כשרים, Ksherim, then it's
כשר Kasher because interestingly it's not that it has to be in
this state when it's offered, it has to actually be... you have
to be מקיים Mekayem the מצוה Mitzvah of בלילה. Blila. That's the
way the גמרא Gemara phrases it, meaning you have to mix them
with the right proportions. Once you created the dough with the right
proportions, then you can mix it up afterwards and burn them even
though now the proportions shift. Okay so that's what the משנה Mishnah
teaches. The problem is mixing the things up before they've been created
as dough. So basically I guess you have here a pile of
flour with some oil dumped on it, but you haven't actually mixed
it together to make dough. And you have another pile of flour
with oil dumped on it in a different proportion. That if you
mix together, now you've got a problem because you have not created
the dough correctly. But once you create the dough correctly then you
can mix it up afterwards. So אם בללם אלו בפני עצמן ואלו
בפני עצמן ונתערבו, Im b'lalam elu bifnei atzman v'elu bifnei atzman v'nitarvu,
and then they got mixed up. כשרים, Ksherim, then it is כשר.
Kasher.
אם עד שלא בלל,
Im
ad shelo balal, however if it got mixed up before it got
mixed, פסול, Pasul, that's invalid and that's what we said before if
the proportions are different. הכבש הבא עם העומר, Hakeves haba im ha'omer,
now the lamb that came with the עומר, Omer, you bring a
lamb קרבן Korban with the עומר Omer and you bring with that
its own מנחה, Mincha, not the עומר. Omer. אף על פי שמנחתו
כפולה, Af al pi sheminchato kfula, although you have double the size
of the מנחה, Mincha, the תורה Torah says you bring שני עשרונים
Shnei esronim for that lamb, not just one. לא היו נסכיו כפולים,
Lo hayu nischav kfulim, you would not double the amount of wine
or oil. So although there's a debate before about whether you shift
in terms of proportion, when it comes to the lamb with the
עומר, Omer, everybody agrees that although the תורה Torah says שני עשרונים,
Shnei esronim, the amount of oil and wine would remain the same.
That's a totally different הלכה. Halacha. Okay so let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara. ורמינהו, U'reminhu, the גמרא Gemara says I'll ask
you on this, this idea about mixing up the מנחות Minchot together.
The פסוק Pasuk says והקטירו: Vehiktiru: you shall offer, burn it, so
it's in the singular, שלא יערב חלבים בחלבים: Shelo yearev chalavim b'chalavim:
do not mix up fats with fats. Okay, that's talking about burning
the fats. Don't mix up fats of one sacrifice with fat of
another. אמר רב יוחנן: Amar Rabbi Yochanan: אי נתערבו, ee nitarvu, so
and presumably if you don't mix up fats with fats, you don't
mix up מנחות minchos with מנחות. minchos. Anything that you burn, you're
supposed to burn separately. You're not supposed to burn them together. Don't
mix up two different sacrifices. So how does our משנה mishna say
that you are allowed to mix up מנחות minchos that have similar
proportions? So the גמרא Gemara answers, אמר רב יוחנן: Amar Rabbi Yochanan:
אי נתערבו כאמר: Ee nitarvu ka'amar: if you mixed it up. It
doesn't say you're allowed to, it says if. Now of course it
doesn't sound that way, because the whole משנה mishna says you can
do it, and then it says בדיעבד bedieved actually there are some
cases where it would even be okay even in the other case.
So it sounds like you can do it לכתחילה. lechatchila. So the
גמרא Gemara is going to object to that. אי הכי, Ee hachi,
if that's how you're reading the משנה, mishna, ואין מערבין נסכי כבשים
בנסכי פרים ואילים, ve'ein mearvin niskei kvasim b'niskei parim v'eilim, it says
you do not mix lamb with rams and oxen. So ואפילו נתערבו
נמי לא? v'afillu nitarvu nami lo? So you're reading the משנה mishna
what it says do it and don't do it, it means בדיעבד.
bedieved. So if it says don't mix lambs with the other ones,
then it's saying that according to your read of בדיעבד, bedieved, it's
saying that בדיעבד bedieved it would be no good. But that's not
true. והא מדקתני סיפא, v'ha midektani seifa, the end of the משנה
mishna says: באו אלו בפני עצמן ואלו בפני עצמן ונתערבו כשרים. bau
elu bifnei atzman v'elu bifnei atzman v'nitarvu ksherim. If you first mixed
them separately and then mixed them together, it's כשר. kosher. So you
see that בדיעבד bedieved it is okay. מכלל דרישא לכתחילה קאמר. miklal
d'reisha lechatchila ka'amar. When our משנה mishna says you mix them, it
doesn't mean בדיעבד, bedieved, it means לכתחילה lechatchila you mix them. Okay,
so we're basically, it was a little difficult way to prove it,
but the point is the end of the משנה mishna is talking
about בדיעבד, bedieved, clearly the beginning of the משנה mishna is talking
about לכתחילה. lechatchila. So our משנה mishna says לכתחילה lechatchila you can
mix up מנחות. minchos. How does this fit with our principle that
when you burn things on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, you're supposed to burn
each קרבן korban separately? So אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, so אביי Abaye
says: הכי קאמר: hachi ka'amar: מערבין יינם אי נתערבו סלתם ושמנם. mearvin
yeinam ee nitarvu soltam v'shamnam. So אביי Abaye says like this, look.
There's one thing that you're allowed to mix up. What are you
allowed to mix up? Wine. Why are you allowed to mix up
wine? Because this idea that you have to burn things separately from
the פסוק pasuk is והקטירו, vehiktiru, is talking about הקטרה, haktara, burning.
So wine which you don't burn, you're allowed to mix up the
wine of different sacrifices. The only concern אביי Abaye would say is
that if you're going to let me mix up the wine of
different sacrifices, I'm going to come to mix up the מנחות minchos
of different sacrifices, I'm not going to make a distinction. So therefore
normally we don't let you mix up the wine of different sacrifices.
But here, the way to read the משנה mishna is, it's a
very forced read of the משנה, mishna, when the משנה mishna says
you can mix up the מנחה mincha of these different things, it
really means you can mix up the wines of these different things
if you already mixed up the מנחה. mincha. Since if you've already
mixed it up and now it's כשר kosher anyway and anyway they're
the same proportion. Right, you're not allowed to mix up the מנחה,
mincha, but if you did, it's לכתחילה... lechatchila... right, now actually, right,
now actually it's not such a terrible read, you know why? Because
our משנה mishna speaks about being מערב meariev the נסכים, nesachim, נסכי,
niskei, so we said when we read the משנה, mishna, it meant
the מנחה mincha of מנחת נסכים. minchat nesachim. But actually, according to
אביי, Abaye, it's not a bad point, you can mix up the
wine since even were you to mix up the מנחות, minchos, they
would actually be the same proportions. So that's the way אביי Abaye
is reading it. So let's take a look. הכי קאמר: hachi ka'amar:
מערבין יינם, mearvin yeinam, you can mix up their wine, אי נתערבו
סלתם ושמנם, ee nitarvu soltam v'shamnam, if the thing actually already got
mixed up, since they were the same proportion anyway, then you might
as well mix up the wines and anyway what do we have
to be concerned about? So the גמרא Gemara says: ויינם לכתחילה לא?
v'yeinam lechatchila lo? Are you telling me לכתחילה lechatchila you're not allowed
to? והתניא, v'hatanya, we taught in a ברייתא: braisa: במה דברים אמורים
בסלת ושמן, bameh devarim amurim besoles v'shemen, when do you have to
burn things separately, when it's talking about flour and oil? אבל יין
מערבין, aval yayin mearvin, wine you can mix up even לכתחילה. lechatchila.
אלא אמר אביי, Ela amar Abaye, so he's going to say the
same thing with a slight nuance. הכי קאמר: hachi ka'amar: היכא דהוקטר
סלת ושמן מערבין יינם לכתחילה. heicha d'hoktar soles v'shemen mearvin yeinam lechatchila.
No, he's going to insist on the same point. We don't let
you mix up wine לכתחילה lechatchila because you'll come to mix up
the flour and the oil as you know, the flour and the
oil. But there are two scenarios where we don't have to make
the גזירה. gezeira. One scenario is that you've already burned the flour
and the oil, so therefore there's no concern you'll mix them up.
And the other scenario is you've already mixed them up. Okay, right,
you get that those are the two scenarios we don't have to
be concerned about what's going to happen. One is because it's already
burned and the other is because it's already mixed up. So when
does the ברייתא braisa say you can mix the wine לכתחילה? lechatchila?
When you've already burned the flour and the oil. Then there's no
concern about mixing anything else up, so go ahead and mix the
wine. היכא דלא הוקטר, heicha d'lo hoktar, if you didn't already burn
them, then we're back to what I was saying originally, says אביי.
Abaye. Then אי נתערבו סלת ושמן מערבין נמי יינם, ee nitarvu soles
v'shemen mearvin nami yeinam, if the flour and oil got mixed up,
then you can mix, that's our משנה mishna that says you can
mix the wine. When can you mix the wine? When the flour
and oil got mixed up as long as they are the same
type of proportion, same type of מנחה. mincha. ואם לאו, v'im lav,
but if the flour and oil didn't In that case אין מערבין
ein me'arvin we do not let you mix up the wine דילמא
אתי לאירובי סולת ושמן לכתחילה dilma ati le'eruvei solet veshemen lechatchila lest
you come to mix them up. So anyway what we have done
now is we really have I mean it's a hard read of
the משנה mishna getting in all this גזירה gezera but the point
is is that it's an interesting question about do you have to
keep the sacrifices separate when you put them on the מזבח mizbe'ach
and the assumption is based on our משנה mishna sounds like no
but we have modified it based on these ברייתות braitot to say
yes you have to burn things separately only the wine can be
mixed up but there are certain בדיעבד bedi'avad situations if it happens
to get mixed up you are allowed to burn them as long
as the proportions are the same. Okay. Interestingly the גמרא gemara chooses
not to discuss the second part of the משנה mishna which is
that you make these doughs separate that it's all about not how
you burn it but how you make it. Once you've made the
dough correctly and then you mix up the doughs that's okay even
though the proportions change the key is how you made the dough.
And now we shift our attention into the last part of the
משנה mishna about the lamb of the that comes with the עומר
omer where there you bring a what do you call it you
bring a מנחה mincha but it's double the amount of flour and
that's in the פסוקים. pesukim. So let's take a look. כבש הבא
עם העומר. keves haba im ha'omer. תנו רבנן tanu rabanan ומנחתו uminchato
the מנחה mincha of this lamb not the עומר omer the מנחה
mincha of the lamb שני עשרונים shenei esronim is two עשרונים. esronim.
לימד על כבש limed al keves says the ברייתא braita teaches you
about the lamb הבא עם העומר haba im ha'omer שמנחתו כפולה sheminchato
kfula you have twice as much flour. יכול כשם שמנחתו כפולה כך
יינו כפול yachol keshem sheminchato kfula kach yeino kaful maybe the same
way the amount of flour is doubled you'll double the amount of
wine? תלמוד לומר talmud lomar so the פסוק pasuk writes there and
says ונסכו יין רביעית ההין venisko yayin revi'it hahin the wine is
a quarter of a הין hin it's שלשה לוגין shelosha login the
standard amount. יכול לא יהיה יינו כפול שאין נבלל עם מנחתו yachol
lo yiheye yeino kaful she'ein nivlal im minchato I understand that you
don't double the wine because that's not part of the very מנחה
mincha itself you don't mix it with the flour אבל יהיה שמנו
כפול שנבלל עם מנחתו aval yiheye shamno kaful shenivlal im minchato but
the oil should be doubled because that's mixed which makes a lot
of sense right and that's our general principle the general principle of
the חכמים chachamim is if you have more flour you have more
oil. So here when the תורה torah says you have twice as
much flour maybe you have twice as much oil? תלמוד לומר ונסכו
talmud lomar u'nisko and its and its libation כל נסכיו kol nishkav
all of its liquids you know whether it's the wine or the
or the oil לא יהיה אלא רביעית lo yiheye ela revi'it are
limited to a רביעית. revi'it. רבי יוחנן אמר ונסכו יין. Rabbi Yochanan
amar venisko yayin. One minute. הגמרא hagemara says no no מאי תלמודא
mai talmuda where are you getting that from the פסוק pasuk says
the גמרא gemara because if anything ונסכו unisko means you know singular
its נסך nesech one and not multiple. So אמר רבי אלעזר amar
Rabbi Elazar כתיב ונסכה ktiv u'nishkah it's written with a hey ונסכה
u'nishkah וקרינן ונסכו. u'karinan u'nisko. Okay כיצד keitzad how do you explain
the hey the way it's written and the way it's read? נסכה
דמנחה כנסכו דיין nishkah demincha kenisko deyayin the feminine the נסכה nishkah
of the מנחה mincha is like the נסכו nisko of the wine.
So what is the libation of the מנחה? mincha? What is the
liquid of the מנחה? mincha? It's the oil. So the oil of
the מנחה mincha the נסכה nishkah and the נסכו nisko are the
same. The נסכה nishkah and the נסכו nisko are both the רביעית
ההין revi'it hahin and those do not change their proportions. מה יין
רביעית אף שמן נמי רביעית. ma yayin revi'it af shemen nami revi'it.
Okay very good. So that's how we get that you do not
change the oil or the wine even though the flour has and
as opposed to other מנחות menachot where if you're going to give
more flour you would give according to the חכמים chachamim more oil.
Now we turn on to move away from the משנה mishna and
have a little discussion about this about well we'll see about things
that relate to their נסך. nesech. Let's take a look. אמר רבי
יוחנן amar Rabbi Yochanan אשם מצורע ששחטו שלא לשמו asham metzora sheshachato
shelo lishmo טעון נסכים. taun nesachim. So you have an אשם asham
of a מצורע metzora that you שחט shachat it שלא לשמו. shelo
lishmo. Now what's the הלכה? halacha? When you שחט shachat an אשם
שלא לשמו asham shelo lishmo we say כל קרבנות kol korbanot you
know all קרבנות korbanot that are done שלא לשמו shelo lishmo except
for a חטאת chatat they're כשר kasher but they לא עלו לבעלים
לשם חובה. lo alu livalim leshem chova. Okay now we've got now
he says you have to now by a מצורע metzora it's normally
with an אשם asham you do not bring נסכים. nesachim. The normal
rule is that you only bring נסכים nesachim with an עולה ola
or a שלמים shelamim something that could come in the form of
a free will even if it's a חובה. chova. An אשם asham
you do not bring נסכים. nesachim. But by the תורה torah what
it says by the מצורע metzora as we just read before there's
a מנחה mincha that comes with the מצורע metzora which right so
therefore he's calling it the נסכים. nesachim. So therefore if you bring
that if you שחט shachat the אשם asham שלא לשמו shelo lishmo
you still have to bring that מנחה. mincha. That's what he says.
טעון נסכים. taun nesachim. שאם אי אתה אומר כן she'im ee ata
omer ken because if you don't say that פסלתו pasalto you'll make
it פסול pasul because it'll be the אשם מצורע asham metzora without
its מנחה. mincha. So therefore you would have invalidated it. So even
though it's not going to work for the מצורע metzora since it
still is starting as an אשם asham of a מצורע metzora and
it's still good as a קרבן korban even though the person isn't
יוצא yotzei so the requirement of an אשם asham of a מצורע
metzora is that it comes with this מנחה. mincha. So מתיב ליה
רב מנשיה בר גדא. mative lei Rav Menashya bar Gada. You can't
say that because now this is fascinating you know it's always great
or interesting When we've gone through all of מסכת זבחים Masechet Zevachim
and some key discussion is missing there to sort of clarify what's
going on. So the key question that comes when you say when
you bring something שלא לשמו, shelo lishmo, it's a good קרבן korban
but it doesn't count for the owner is: how much has the
identity
of the קרבן korban shifted? Right?
So if I'm bringing something as an עולה olah and now it's
done שלא לשמו shelo lishmo and it's good but it doesn't count
for me, you know, is it still an עולה, olah, it's still
the same type of an עולה? olah? And then normally that's a
pretty, obviously we know you burn it fully and you treat it
as an עולה, olah, so normally it's not such an interesting question.
But let's look about it when you say an אשם. asham. That
is an interesting question because, you know, the whole idea that an
אשם asham that's not working for the בעלים be'alim can still be
a good קרבן korban is pretty amazing. We don't say that by
a חטאת. chatas. So how is this now being brought? Is this
being brought as an אשם, asham, as a generic אשם? asham? What
does an אשם asham mean if it's not coming for an obligation?
So that is essentially what's being explored here. This אשם מצורע asham
metzora that is not working for the מצורע, metzora, does it still
identify as an אשם asham of a מצורע metzora or does it
become something more generic? So the first opinion is it still identified
as an אשם asham of a מצורע, metzora, and an אשם מצורע
asham metzora without the מנחה mincha is invalid. Okay, and that is
what the גמרא's Gemara really questioning. But if it's working without satisfying
the obligation, maybe you can't call it an אשם מצורע asham metzora
anymore. Let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says מתקיף לה
רב מנשה בר גדתא, matkif leh Rav Menashe bar Gadata, אלא מעתה
ela me'atah if you say that, כבש הבא עם העומר—now keves habah
im ha'omer this is why we're bringing it in here because the
משנה Mishna mentioned the lamb that comes with the עומר—ששחטו שלא לשמו,
shelo lishmo, if he slaughtered it שלא לשמו, shelo lishmo תהא מנחתו
כפולה, tehei minchato kefuloh, you would have to bring with that a
double מנחה mincha because it would still be identified as the עומר
omer lamb. Okay? שאם אי אתה אומר כן פסלתו, she'im ee attah
omer ken psalto, because or else you'd invalidate it. You're saying that
even שלא לשמו shelo lishmo, it is still fully identified in its
original form, it's with its original identity. So demand a double מנחה.
mincha. ותמיד של שחר ששחטו שלא לשמו, vesamid shel shachar sheshachato shelo
lishmo, and if you brought a תמיד, tamid, the morning תמיד, tamid,
and you did it שלא לשמו, shelo lishmo, יהא טעון שני גזירים
ושני כהנים, yehei taun shenei gezirim ushenei kohanim, you would have to
bring the two, the two, you know, logs of wood that you
bring together with the תמיד. tamid. Now that's a little funny that
normally you'd assume maybe you do them at the same time but
not that conceptually it's part of the bringing of the תמיד. tamid.
But anyway that's at least the way the גמרא Gemara is saying
it. שאם אי אתה אומר כן פסלתו, she'im ee attah omer ken
psalto, because otherwise you'd invalidate it, that has to be how the
תמיד tamid is brought. ותמיד של בין הערבים ששחטו שלא לשמו, vesamid
shel bein ha'arbayim sheshachato shelo lishmo, or the afternoon תמיד tamid that
you did שלא לשמו, shelo lishmo, יהא טעון שני גזירים ושני כהנים,
yehei taun shenei gezirim ushenei kohanim, same two logs except now with
two כהנים. kohanim. שאם אי אתה אומר כן פסלת, she'im ee attah
omer ken pasalta, because otherwise you'd invalidate. So, context, by the way,
what's fascinating parenthetically is the assumption that these logs of wood are
an essential part of the תמיד. tamid. Okay, but anyway the גמרא
Gemara is now basically what he's bothering him is he's saying, look,
as soon as you do it שלא לשמו, shelo lishmo, it does
not have its original identity, okay? It's generic אשם, asham, it's generic
עולה, olah, and therefore it goes to whatever that general law is.
So an אשם asham generically does not get a מנחה, mincha, okay?
Or if the lambs of the עומר omer were שלא לשמו, shelo
lishmo so they're generic and they do get their normal נסכים, nesachim,
they don't get the—I mean their normal מנחה, mincha, not their double
מנחה, mincha, and that's what happens. It does not retain its earlier
identity. But the גמרא Gemara is going—is insisting on it. We'll see
the full answer tomorrow, but we'll just read the initial thing. First
answer is אין הכי נמי. ein hachi nami. You gotta love it.
One man's reductio ad absurdum is another man's אין הכי נמי. ein
hachi nami. You have it right there. Just: What? You mean in
all these cases you have to do that? And it's like: Yeah,
אין הכי נמי. ein hachi nami. Yes, I say that even שלא
לשמו shelo lishmo. it retains its identity and therefore you have to
do it exactly the way you would have done it initially and
if not, you invalidate it. Tomorrow we're going to see אביי Abaye
who is going to disagree with that and say no, it shifts
identity when it's שלא לשמו.